Guide to the Governor's Original Mansion Restoration Society Advisory Council records 1970-2009
Montana Historical Society
Governor's Original Mansion Restoration Society Advisory Council records,
1970-2009
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 390 (17:3-5)
Governor's Original Mansion Restoration Society Advisory Council
.8 linear feet
This collection consists of records created by the Governor's Original Mansion Restoration Society Advisory Council, and includes correspondence, financial records, minutes, organizational, reports, subject files, and miscellany.
Administrative Note
In 1959 Governor Hugo Aaronson vacated the 1888 Queen Anne Mansion at 304 Ewing Street, and moved to the new Executive Mansion at 2 Carson Street. Originally, the Helena Chamber of Commerce undertook the historic preservation and restoration of the old mansion. Soon however, Helena Mayor Dave Lewis and the City Commission negotiated for the Mansion to be leased to the City of Helena so that it could be restored and maintained as a historic museum. To oversee this effort, in 1969 Mayor Lewis appointed the Governors' Old Mansion Restoration Committee. The committee consisted of the following people: Mr. Joe A Maierle (Chairman), Mr. John Schroeder (Co-Chairman), Mr. George Schotte, Mr. Lester Loble II, Mrs. Sherman W. Smith, Mayor Dave Lewis (Ex-Officio member), Mrs. Tim Babcock, Mrs. Sam C. Ford, Mrs. Forrest Anderso, Mrs. Fred Gannon, and Mrs. J.R. Kaiserman.
In 1969, the Legislative Assembly appropriated thirty-five thousand dollars towards initial repairs of the building; these funds were used to restore the exterior. To supplement these funds, the City of Helena filed an application with the Department of Housing and Urban Development for a Historic Preservation Grant, and the Committee worked to secure funds from donors around the State. The Committee and the Chamber also introduced a bill into the 1971 Legislative Assembly for an additional thirty-nine thousand dollars to match Federal funds to complete the restoration at a cost of seventy-eight thousand dollars.
By 1980 the City of Helena was unable to continue management of the Mansion financially. The State terminated the lease to the city and the Montana Historical Society (MHS) took responsibility for restoration, maintenance and management of the Mansion. The Mansion Committee continued to function as the policy and management authority, consistent with the overall policies of the MHS, while the Governors' Original Mansion Restoration Society Board's primary function was to act as a fund-raising entity and sponsor annual events to raise money. The Secret Garden Tour, created in 2005, is now the main fund raising effort of the Original Governor's Mansion Restoration Society Board (now called the Governors' Original Mansion Restoration Society Advisory Council), a volunteer group of Montana citizens dedicated to OGM restoration projects.
This collection consists of correspondence (1973-1981); financial records (1973-1977, 1980), which include quotations for the purchase of furnishings, and accounts payable receipts; minutes (1974-2009); organizational records (1974-1980), including by-laws of the Board/Advisory Council and official register of board members; reports (1975-1976, 1978-1980), including committee reports and monthly reports; subject files (1970, 1974-1978), including Master Plan for Interior Restoration, Specifications for Exterior Restoration, Original Governor's Mansion research materials, and inventory of Mansion furnishings, and contract materials; and miscellany (1978, 1979), including newsletter and Old House Heritage Tour.
Arranged by series.
Collection is open for research
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Historic Buildings--Montana--Helena.
Historic Preservation.
Original Governor's Mansion (Helena, Mont.).
Helena, Mont.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Correspondence
  - General (Correspondents include: Joe Marierle, Betty Babcock, Don Harriott, Mike Mansfield, John J. McLaughlin, and John N. DeHaas), 1973-1975 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - General (Correspondents include: Robert Archibald, Carol Harrison, Campeau & Crennen, Harriet Meloy, Raymond L. Beaver, Shirley Gannon, Mary Holtz, and A.W. Scribner), 1976-1981 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Financial Records
  - Accounts Payable, 1975 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Budget Material, 1974-1977, 1980 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - "Quotations" [Price quotes for furnishings], 1973-1975 (Box-folder 1/5)
- Minutes
  - Meeting Minutes [includes associated materials], 1974-1978 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Meeting Minutes [includes associated materials], 1976-1977 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Meeting Minutes [includes associated materials], 1977-1978 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Meeting Minutes [includes associated materials], 1978-1979 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Meeting Minutes [includes associated materials], 1980-1981, December 1983 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Meeting Minutes [includes associated materials], 2001-2003 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Meeting Minutes [includes associated materials], 2004-2009 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Meeting Minutes [executive committee and Original Governor's Mansion board of trustees], 1980 (Box-folder 2/3)
- Organizational
  - By-laws and Official Register of Board Members, 1974-1980 (Box-folder 2/4)
- Reports
  - Committee and Monthly, 1975-1976, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 2/5)
- Subject Files
  - Master plan for interior restoration; Specifications for exterior restoration; Master Plan for Restoration of the Governors Original Mansion City of Helena, Montana, n.d., 1970, 1975 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - "Contract - Copy of Opal Smith and City of Helena", 1974 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - "Governor's Old Mansion - Research", 1974-1978 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - "Inventory - Furnishings list", 1974 (Box-folder 2/9)
- Miscellany
  - "Original Governor's Mansion," newsletter, Old House Club Heritage Tour, n.d., 1978, 1979 (Box-folder 2/10)